I grew up in a very small country town in Victoria. I had a very normal, low-key kind of upbringing. I went to school, I hung out with my friends, I fought with my younger sisters. It was all very normal. And when I was 15, a member of my local community approached my parents and wanted to nominate me for a community achievement award. And my parents said, "Hm, that's really nice, but there's kind of one glaring problem with that. She hasn't actually achieved anything." (Laughter) And they were right, you know. I went to school, I got good marks, I had a very low-key after school job in my mum's hairdressing salon, and I spent a lot of time watching "Buffy the Vampire Slayer" and "Dawson's Creek." Yeah, I know. What a contradiction. But they were right, you know. I wasn't doing anything that was out of the ordinary at all. I wasn't doing anything that could be considered an achievement if you took disability out of the equation. Years later, I was on my second teaching round in a Melbourne high school, and I was about 20 minutes into a year 11 legal studies class when this boy put up his hand and said, "Hey miss, when are you going to start doing your speech?" And I said, "What speech?" You know, I'd been talking them about defamation law for a good 20 minutes. And he said, "You know, like, your motivational speaking. You know, when people in wheelchairs come to school, they usually say, like, inspirational stuff?" (Laughter) "It's usually in the big hall." And that's when it dawned on me: This kid had only ever experienced disabled people as objects of inspiration. We are not, to this kid -- and it's not his fault, I mean, that's true for many of us. For lots of us, disabled people are not our teachers or our doctors or our manicurists. We're not real people. We are there to inspire. And in fact, I am sitting on this stage looking like I do in this wheelchair, and you are probably kind of expecting me to inspire you. Right? (Laughter) Yeah. Well, ladies and gentlemen, I'm afraid I'm going to disappoint you dramatically. I am not here to inspire you. I am here to tell you that we have been lied to about disability. Yeah, we've been sold the lie that disability is a Bad Thing, capital B, capital T. It's a bad thing, and to live with a disability makes you exceptional. It's not a bad thing, and it doesn't make you exceptional. And in the past few years, we've been able to propagate this lie even further via social media. You may have seen images like this one: "The only disability in life is a bad attitude." Or this one: "Your excuse is invalid." Indeed. Or this one: "Before you quit, try!" These are just a couple of examples, but there are a lot of these images out there. You know, you might have seen the one, the little girl with no hands drawing a picture with a pencil held in her mouth. You might have seen a child running on carbon fiber prosthetic legs. And these images, there are lots of them out there, they are what we call inspiration porn. (Laughter) And I use the term porn deliberately, because they objectify one group of people for the benefit of another group of people. So in this case, we're objectifying disabled people for the benefit of nondisabled people. The purpose of these images is to inspire you, to motivate you, so that we can look at them and think, "Well, however bad my life is, it could be worse. I could be that person." But what if you are that person? I've lost count of the number of times that I've been approached by strangers wanting to tell me that they think I'm brave or inspirational, and this was long before my work had any kind of public profile. They were just kind of congratulating me for managing to get up in the morning and remember my own name. (Laughter) And it is objectifying. These images, those images objectify disabled people for the benefit of nondisabled people. They are there so that you can look at them and think that things aren't so bad for you, to put your worries into perspective. And life as a disabled person is actually somewhat difficult. We do overcome some things. But the things that we're overcoming are not the things that you think they are. They are not things to do with our bodies. I use the term "disabled people" quite deliberately, because I subscribe to what's called the social model of disability, which tells us that we are more disabled by the society that we live in than by our bodies and our diagnoses. So I have lived in this body a long time. I'm quite fond of it. It does the things that I need it to do, and I've learned to use it to the best of its capacity just as you have, and that's the thing about those kids in those pictures as well. They're not doing anything out of the ordinary. They are just using their bodies to the best of their capacity. So is it really fair to objectify them in the way that we do, to share those images? People, when they say, "You're an inspiration," they mean it as a compliment. And I know why it happens. It's because of the lie, it's because we've been sold this lie that disability makes you exceptional. And it honestly doesn't. And I know what you're thinking. You know, I'm up here bagging out inspiration, and you're thinking, "Jeez, Stella, aren't you inspired sometimes by some things?" And the thing is, I am. I learn from other disabled people all the time. I'm learning not that I am luckier than them, though. I am learning that it's a genius idea to use a pair of barbecue tongs to pick up things that you dropped. (Laughter) I'm learning that nifty trick where you can charge your mobile phone battery from your chair battery. Genius. We are learning from each others' strength and endurance, not against our bodies and our diagnoses, but against a world that exceptionalizes and objectifies us. I really think that this lie that we've been sold about disability is the greatest injustice. It makes life hard for us. And that quote, "The only disability in life is a bad attitude," the reason that that's bullshit is because it's just not true, because of the social model of disability. No amount of smiling at a flight of stairs has ever made it turn into a ramp. Never. (Laughter) (Applause) Smiling at a television screen isn't going to make closed captions appear for people who are deaf. No amount of standing in the middle of a bookshop and radiating a positive attitude is going to turn all those books into braille. It's just not going to happen. I really want to live in a world where disability is not the exception, but the norm. I want to live in a world where a 15-year-old girl sitting in her bedroom watching "Buffy the Vampire Slayer" isn't referred to as achieving anything because she's doing it sitting down. I want to live in a world where we don't have such low expectations of disabled people that we are congratulated for getting out of bed and remembering our own names in the morning. I want to live in a world where we value genuine achievement for disabled people, and I want to live in a world where a kid in year 11 in a Melbourne high school is not one bit surprised that his new teacher is a wheelchair user. Disability doesn't make you exceptional, but questioning what you think you know about it does. Thank you. (Applause)
Crecí en un pequeño pueblo rural en Victoria. Tenía un perfil muy normal, un bajo perfil de educación. Fui a la escuela, me juntaba con mis amigos, me peleaba con mis hermanas menores. Todo era muy normal. Y cuando tenía 15 años, un miembro de mi comunidad se acercó a mis padres porque quería nominarme para un premio de la comunidad. Y mis padres dijeron: "Bien, eso es muy bonito, pero existe un problema evidente. Ella en realidad no ha conseguido nada". (Risas) Y tenían razón. Fui a la escuela, tenía buenas notas. Tras la escuela, yo tenía un bajo perfil en la peluquería de mi madre, y pasaba mucho tiempo mirando las series "Buffy the Vampire Slayer" y "Dawson's Creek". Sí, lo sé. Qué contradicción. Pero tenían razón. Yo no hacía nada que fuera extraordinario en absoluto. Nada que pueda considerarse como un logro si tomamos la discapacidad fuera de la ecuación. Años más tarde, estando en la segunda parte de la enseñanza en una escuela secundaria de Melbourne, tan solo tras unos 20 minutos en la clase 11 de estudios jurídicos un muchacho levantó la mano y dijo: "Oye, ¿cuándo darás tu discurso?" Y yo: "¿Qué discurso?" Bueno, yo les había estado hablando sobre la ley de difamación por unos buenos 20 minutos. Y él dijo: "Ya sabes, tu discurso motivacional. Cuando las personas en sillas de ruedas, hablan de cosas inspiracionales en la escuela?" (Risas) "Por lo general, en el salón de actos". Y fue entonces cuando me di cuenta: Este niño había tenido experiencias con personas con discapacidad como objetos de inspiración. Y no lo somos. Y no es culpa del muchacho, es decir, eso es cierto para muchos de nosotros. Para nosotros, las personas con discapacidad no son nuestros maestros o nuestros médicos o nuestras manicuristas. No somos personas reales. Estamos allí para inspirar. Y, de hecho, estoy en este escenario pareciéndose a lo que hago en esta silla de ruedas, y probablemente Uds. estén esperando a que les inspire. ¿Cierto? (Risas) Sí. Bueno, señoras y señores, me temo decepcionarles estrepitosamente. No estoy aquí para inspirarles. Estoy aquí para decirles que nos han mentido en relación a la discapacidad. Sí, nos han vendido la mentira de que la discapacidad es Algo Malo, A mayúscula, M mayúscula. Es algo malo y vivir con una discapacidad te hace excepcional. No es algo malo y no logra hacerte excepcional. Y en los últimos años, hemos podido propagar aún más esta mentira a través de medios de comunicación social. Es posible que hayan visto imágenes como ésta: "La única discapacidad en la vida es una mala actitud". O esta otra: "Su excusa es inválida". En efecto. O esta otra: "Antes de abandonar, ¡inténtelo!" Estos son sólo un par de ejemplos, pero existe una gran cantidad de ellos. Puede ser que hayan visto uno, de la niña sin manos dibujando con un lápiz sostenido por la boca. Puede que hayan visto a un niño que corre con piernas ortopédicas de fibra de carbono. Y hay un montón de estas imágenes, que son lo que llamamos inspiración porno. (Risas) Y uso el término porno deliberadamente, ya que cosifican a un grupo de personas para el beneficio de otro grupo de personas. Así que en este caso, cosificamos a los discapacitados en beneficio de las personas sin discapacidad. El propósito de estas imágenes es inspirarlos, motivarlos, para que podamos verlos y pensar: "Bueno, por muy mala que sea mi vida, podría ser peor. Yo podría ser esa persona". Pero ¿y si eres esa persona? He perdido la cuenta del número de veces que me han abordado extraños queriéndome expresar que creen que yo soy valiente o una fuente de inspiración, y esto sucedía a antes de que mi trabajo tuviera un perfil público. Era como si me felicitaran por levantarme por la mañana y recordar mi propio nombre. (Risas) Y esto es cosificar. Estas imágenes, esas imágenes cosifican a las personas con discapacidad en beneficio de las personas sin discapacidad. Están ahí para que Uds. puedan verlas y pensar que las cosas no son tan malas para Uds., o para poner sus preocupaciones en perspectiva. Y la vida como persona discapacitada es en realidad algo difícil. Superamos algunas cosas. Pero las cosas que superamos no son las cosas en las que Uds. puedan pensar. No son cosas relativas a nuestros cuerpos. Yo uso el término "personas discapacitadas", deliberadamente porque me suscribo al llamado modelo social de la discapacidad, que nos dice que somos más discapacitados debido a la sociedad en que vivimos que debido a nuestros cuerpos o diagnósticos. Así que he vivido en este cuerpo por mucho tiempo. Estoy muy encariñada con él. Hace las cosas que necesito que haga, y he aprendido a sacar lo mejor de su capacidad así como Uds. lo hacen, y eso es lo que pasa con los niños de esas fotos también. No están haciendo nada fuera de lo común. Ellos simplemente están usando sus cuerpos sacando lo mejor de su capacidad. Entonces, ¿es realmente justo cosificarlos en la forma que lo hacemos, al compartir esas imágenes? Cuando la gente nos dice: "Eres una fuente de inspiración" lo dice como un cumplido. Y sé por qué sucede. Es a causa de la mentira, porque nos han vendido esta mentira de que la discapacidad nos hace excepcionales. Y, honestamente, no lo hace. Y sé lo que están pensando. Estoy aquí boicoteando la inspiración, y Uds. piensan: "Por Dios, Stella, ¿no estás a veces inspirada por algo?" Y en realidad, sí que lo estoy. Aprendo de otras personas con discapacidad en todo momento. Sin embargo, no aprendo que soy más afortunada que ellos. Aprendo que se trata de una idea genial usar unas pinzas de barbacoa para recoger las cosas que se me caen. (Risas) Aprendo el ingenioso truco de cómo cargar la batería del teléfono móvil en la batería de la silla. Genial. Aprendemos de la fuerza y resistencia de los demás, no contra nuestros cuerpos y nuestros diagnósticos, sino contra un mundo que excepcionaliza y nos cosifica. Realmente creo que esa mentira que nos han vendido acerca de la discapacidad es la mayor injusticia, nos hace la vida difícil. Y esa cita: "La única discapacidad en la vida es una mala actitud", la razón de que eso es mentira se debe a que no es verdadera, debido al modelo social de discapacidad. Un montón de sonrisas ante un tramo de escaleras no ha hecho nunca que se convierta en una rampa. Nunca. (Risas) (Aplausos) Sonreir ante una pantalla de televisión no hará aparecer los subtítulos para las personas sordas. Tampoco un montón de gente en medio de una librería e irradiando una actitud positiva convertirá todos esos libros al braille. Simplemente no va a suceder. Quiero realmente vivir en un mundo donde la discapacidad no es la excepción, sino la norma. Quiero vivir donde una niña de 15 años, sentada en su dormitorio viendo "Buffy the Vampire Slayer" no se considere no merecedora de nada por estar en una silla. Yo quiero vivir en un mundo donde no tengamos tan bajas expectativas de las personas con discapacidad que seamos felicitados por levantarnos de la cama y recordar nuestros nombres por la mañana. Yo quiero vivir en un mundo donde valoramos el logro genuino de las personas con discapacidad, y yo quiero vivir en un mundo donde un niño del 11º grado en una escuela secundaria de Melbourne no esté ni un poco sorprendido de que su nuevo maestro es un usuario de silla de ruedas. La discapacidad no nos hace excepcionales, pero cuestionar lo que uno cree saber al respecto sí que lo hace. Gracias. (Aplausos)